Welcome back everyone, I hope you are ready to
dive into today's lesson and learn something new.
Today we're going to learn about a quite
challenging question type in the IELTS reading test.
True, false or not given.
However, don't worry guys, today we're going to tackle it together.
This lesson aims to help you understand and identify
features of true, false or not given questions and answers.
Understand and apply steps for true, false or not given questions.
Alright, no more delay, let's begin.
First of all, let's explore the features
of the true, false or not given questions.
This question type often appears in reading passage 1 and 2 of the test.
The thing that helps you identify this question type is the question, do the
following statements agree with the information given in the reading passage?
So this question type requires candidates to identify whether statements in
questions agree or disagree with the information
in the reading passage or are not mentioned.
Let's take a closer look at an example to
understand the structure of this question type.
The question type has two parts.
The first one is the requirements requiring candidates to identify whether
given statements are true, false or not given.
The second one is the numbered statements.
For this question type, there is a feature that can be considered as an
advantage and helps us handle it more quickly.
It is, these statements come in order as the information in the passage.
This means that if we find the information for statement 1 in the previous line
or paragraph, we can move on to the next line or paragraph to find the
information for the next statement.
So for this question type, finding the
information isn't really time consuming, is it?
Next, we're going to learn how to identify
which information is true, false or not given.
If we can't distinguish these three types of answers,
we won't be able to choose the correct answer.
Distinguish three types of answers, true, false or not given.
1. True.
The statement 100% agrees with the information in the passage.
Firstly, the statement will be true if it 100%
agrees with the information in the passage.
You should note that the statement should 100% agree with the conveyed
information because the keywords in the statement
might not 100% match those of the passage.
Instead, the keywords might be paraphrased.
Speaking of paraphrasing, does anyone remember the techniques for paraphrasing
that I introduced to you?
In case you don't, I'm going to introduce
some techniques for paraphrasing again.
We have four techniques which are called GOSS for short.
Grammar.
Express the same information using different grammatical structures.
Example, change the word form or the active voice to the passive voice.
The first one is paraphrasing using grammar.
For example, keywords can be changed in terms of word form.
Original sentence can be changed from active voice to passive voice.
Order.
Reversing the order of some information in the sentence.
The second technique is called ORDER, which reverses the information order of
some information in the sentence.
We can encounter this technique in sentences that have a feature of listing.
Summary.
Use a collective noun instead of listing all the items.
The third one is summary, in which we use a
collective noun instead of listing all the items.
Synonym.
Use words, phrases or expressions that have
similar meanings to the original sentence.
The final technique is synonym, in which we use words, phrases or expressions
that have a similar meaning to the original sentence.
False.
The statement contradicts the information in the passage.
The statement will be false if it contradicts the information in the passage.
So for false statements, the structures are often small details.
Therefore, I have a tip for you.
Pay attention to details, especially qualifying words, such as Adverbs of
frequency, like often, barely, always, and sometimes Adverbs of probability,
like likely and probably Quantifiers, like some, many, and a few Adverbs
indicating exclusivity, like purely, solely, only Unique, and mainly Modal
verbs, like can, could, should, and must
Ordinal numbers, like first, second, third, etc.
Adjectives of time order, like newest, latest, most recent, or oldest
These words and phrases can completely change the
meaning of the question when compared to the passage.
So pay attention to them to avoid the distractors.
Finally, we're going to learn about the final type of answer that is the most
confusing to the candidates.
Not given.
There is no information on the passage.
This is a difficult type of answer because candidates don't know what
information to find or what information not to find.
Also, it can take them a lot of time to identify
whether the statement is false or not given.
So what is the most important feature of not given statements?
To understand this, we're going to analyze the example in the funny skit.
In 20 seconds, you'll read the following not given statement and guess which
part in the statement is not mentioned in the information area.
20 seconds, start now.
Have you found the answer?
Although the statement includes keywords like bamboo, grow, and grass that are
similar to the topic of the passage, there is a crucial difference.
The passage certainly talks about how fast bamboo grows.
However, it does not mention a comparison regarding
how difficult it is to grow compared to other plants.
It never claims it is the most difficult.
Therefore, a statement is not given when it contains keywords or their
paraphrases from the passage, but the specific relationship or comparison found
in the statement is not mentioned in the text.
It sounds quite simple, but students still mistake not given for true or false.
So why do we easily make mistakes with not given statements?
Let's watch the funny skit again and identify two mistakes that make the
character choose the wrong answer.
The first common mistake is relying on personal knowledge.
For example, you might look at this and think, well, I tried to grow bamboo
once and it died, so it must be difficult.
This assumption leads you to choose true incorrectly.
When taking the actual test, familiar topics can help us understand the
content, but we must never choose an answer based on our own outside knowledge.
We must strictly compare the statement with
the information provided in the passage.
The second common mistake is relying only on keywords.
You might see that bamboo and grow are present in both the text and the
statement, so you immediately assume the answer
is true without checking the full meaning.
By doing this, you miss the fact that the
comparison is missing from the text entirely.
Common mistakes include relying on personal knowledge, relying on keywords.
From these mistakes, what should we do to avoid choosing the wrong answer?
Truly understand the meaning.
Analyze the full content of the statement and the relevant part of the passage,
not just the matching keywords.
Stick to the text.
Do not use personal knowledge to make assumptions or fill in gaps.
Watch for qualifiers.
Pay close attention to comparison words or qualifying
words that might be in the statement but not in the text.
Alright, now that we've understood the features of this question
type, let's move on to part two to learn the steps for it.
To tackle this question type, we need to follow these three steps.
Step one, underline keywords in statements and pay attention to scanning words.
Scanning words are keywords which are found more easily than other keywords,
including unchangeable keywords like proper nouns, acronyms and numbers,
compounds and long words.
Step two, scan passages to locate information
areas containing keywords and their paraphrases.
Step three, read information areas identified in step two carefully to decide
whether these statements are true, false or not given.
Here is a note for you.
You should read the whole statement to understand its
meaning and shouldn't rely completely on keywords.
Now that we have mastered the theory, let's put it into practice.
We are going to apply the three steps we just learned to solve a specific
question based on a reading passage about regulating hate speech.
Let's look at question one.
The United Nations considers any communication
that is simply rude to be a form of hate speech.
Step one, underline keywords in statements and pay attention to scanning words.
First, we need to identify the important words.
Here, United Nations is a proper noun with capital letters, making it an
excellent scanning word because it will be easy to spot in the text.
We also need to underline the content keywords.
Any communication, simply rude and hate speech.
These determine the meaning of the sentence.
Step two, scan passages to locate information areas.
Now, move your eyes quickly over the passage to find United Nations.
Hmm, there it is.
It appears right in the first paragraph.
This is our information area.
Step three, read information areas carefully to decide the answer.
Now we need to compare the statement with the text.
The statement says, the UN considers communication
that is simply rude to be hate speech.
The text says, hate speech is any kind of communication
that attacks or uses discriminatory language.
Experts agree that hate speech is not just about being mean.
Let's analyze this.
Mean and rude are synonyms.
The text explicitly says, hate speech is not just
about being mean, it requires discriminatory language.
Therefore, the statement contradicts the information in the passage.
So the answer for question one is false.
See, by following these steps, we can avoid being tricked by words that look
similar but have different meanings.
Before finishing the lesson, we're going
to quickly recap what we learned today.
After this lesson, we can understand and identify features
of true, false or not given questions and answers.
Understand and apply steps for true, false or not given questions.
Three steps are.
Step one, underline keywords in statements and pay attention to scanning words.
Step two, scan passages to locate information
areas containing keywords and their paraphrases.
Step three, read information areas identified in step two carefully to decide
whether these statements are true, false or not given.
To master them, you need to do practice exercises for this question type.
For now, let's call it a day.
See you in the next lesson.
Goodbye.